good morning and welcome to meditating
the Chandramukhi I'm a cognitive
psychologist and a cognitive scientist
at the University of Toronto where
academically and scientifically study
phenomena like mindfulness related
phenomena like Insight flow mystical
experience transformative experience how
the states of consciousness the
cultivation of wisdom the aspiration
towards enlightenment I've also been
practicing the past of meditation at a
contemplation Tai Chi Chuan she come for
about 29 years and I've been teaching
all of them professionally for close to
20 years most welcome you should know if
you're just joining us for the first
time that this is a progressive course
every Monday is the Dharma day in which
I teach principles and practices that
build on the previous principles and
practices that I've taught if you go to
the description for this video you'll
find links to previous lessons Tuesdays
through Friday we sit trace the Tuesday
so we're set we meet I sometimes do a
bit of review we and then we sit
together at the end of each class Monday
through Friday there is a question and
answer period please direct your
questions just towards this specific
practice or the set of practices on
teaching you're actually for broader
questions you know the philosophical
framework or how this fits into the
cultivation of wisdom or comparing this
to other practices in terms of other
traditions please come to my monthly
live Q&A which we hold on YouTube
livestream 3 p.m. est so we've been
talking about taking the reprocessing of
very very deep past the insight down to
the existential level the level of
identification and what we do for that
is a practice called deepening the pasta
in which we are learning to shift our
focus so what we do is we do the basic
for pasta we're following our breath and
everything's the same
and then we sort of let up we reduce the
effort letter might go the distractions
come up thoughts come up and then we
count our thoughts
we counter thoughts not and the number
is irrelevant we're counting our
thoughts because we're trying to see the
space between their thoughts and then we
try to foreground that space and act on
the thoughts and then we meditate into
that space with the five factors of
employment and this helps us to dis
identify problem are speaking mind it
helps us realize or more open space of
consciousness in their body radically
increase the flexibility the add
activity our consciousness and cognition
and bring to bear on situations when
you're distracted while you're
meditating into that space like a cat
outside of a mouthful label the
distractions with an ing word do the
five factors of aquatic mindfulness note
if the distraction does away with that
feels like an empty mic and then return
to the breath to basic the positive
falling above and that return you get to
a place where that space between your
thoughts become meditative focus and now
what you're trying to do there is you're
trying to sense a thought emerging but
not really go into it and it may not
even fully verbalize it may just for a
bubble of it and then drift away it may
strike you sort of more abstractly and
then drift away and that's what you're
going to meditate on you're going to
meditate on that space that is other
than your speaking and scenic mind
everyone so that's the basic practice
you should always try now after you've
been meditating for a while on like what
you're doing for the past month I'll be
doing that after you've been meditating
asic the pasta for a while follow your
breath then shifting when it seems
appropriate to you into that practice
where you could shift the focus onto
that active space between your spoken
thoughts okay so everybody please set
your phones to do not disturb oh if I
can ask everybody to like this video at
this whole video stream that would be
very helpful because it will raise its
visibility on the YouTube algorithm and
that will help me to promote this
practice for people that I think would
be beneficial for
okay so like I said get comfortable get
at your basic posture
I remember to always find your core for
set your phones I do not disturb and we
will begin when I say begin you get
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can get
greatly to cultivate it in your practice
with your everyday consciousness and
cognition
perhaps by reciting five promises to
yourself
you have time for a few questions just
to remind you that for the next a little
while on Tuesday and Thursday
go through my schedule and my eye shadow
we have to end my ten o'clock nickel is
a gimmick car has a question
I seem to sense the content of the
complete thought before it is verbally
processed through to the end I don't
feel the need to examine it further so I
move on it might be avoided was okay no
that's okay to Matar that's good that
means you're already starting to
separate from the speaking out and then
eventually that conceptual aspect will
also fade away but you're on the right
track so keep going that way and if here
I never knew if I'm thinking in words or
images but during the last few sessions
when watching my monkey mind I've
noticed it depends on what the current
distraction is is that thanks to the six
yes so you're going to get that acuity
that we're training more attractive
treating the five factors of mindless
where everything was just sort of
blogged and confused together that what
this does is it gets you a kind of
acuity and clarity you separate out
different kinds of sensations different
states of mind different emotional
states all of that starts to happen in a
more reliable manner for you so that's
exactly right
that's exactly right test instant I
sometimes tense up in my Rachel to
repeatedly should I relax it or maintain
the stiffness and go through the five on
the stiffness I would go through the
five on the stiffness because if you're
doing repeatedly doing it repeatedly was
repeatedly happening there might be you
know a mental aspect to that that's
driving it and sort of unpacking those
associations might help believing it
rather than just trying to directly
relax it and also because it's a
repeated pattern there is suspicion that
there's probably something deeper going
on there that might be a body honor
aspect for you Nicholas Lamar had
Nicolas when doing normal of a past
night can't we also get into that
in-between space whenever we are between
in and out breath yes you can you can so
some Trish should some traditions in
fact do a three-stage noted you notice
the in-breath caused the space where
there's nothing no motion of body or
light and then the out-breath
pause where there's no motion of body
mind if you find that helpful you can do
that generally giving that for people
initially that's a little too much a
little too demanding in a they start to
really over control the breathing but if
that's happening for you naturally
that's good go with that if you might
want to add it in a little bit more
explicitly like I just said mark the
father great to see you mark much a
strong supporter and participant in the
Sangha is it appropriate desirable good
idea to meditate during something like
acupuncture if so which practices are
best if not why not
so I meditated during all of my tattoos
all of the tattoos I got I'm I was
meditating and that's a very powerful
practice because when there is something
that's very powerful stimulus and
meditating on it that can sort of open
you off in a very powerful way really
help you train your ID activity for
acupuncture these practices and I have
professional training and I practiced
professionally for several years poster
decade as a shiatsu therapist you should
always do you know meditator bar at a
contemplative art of moving art and a
healing art right and then what I all
those practices are about a kind of a
synchrony of mutual mindfulness so
getting into mindfulness would only be
good practice for the mindfulness but it
would also accentuate and help cultivate
the acupuncture okay everyone thank you
very much for joining I want to thank my
good friend and techno sage amar always
behind the scenes making things happen
my beloved son Jason again please like
this video to raise its visibility
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified about notifications they'll
also find on that channel a lot of
relevant videos about mindfulness
meditation and whiteman altered states
of consciousness wisdom responding to
the meeting crisis responding to the
COBIT crisis please invite others who
might benefit from this practice to this
practice I'm trying to reach as many
people what I can with a whole ecology
practices that I think would be very
good for helping increase in a
resiliency our adaptivity our abilities
to
through the crowd and get to what really
matters reminder that we're doing this
every morning at 9:30 est Monday is
Donna day Tuesday through Fridays or six
days and please remember continuity and
practice more important than quantity
there is no enemy greater than your own
mind and there is no ally no friend
greater than your own mind
see you all tomorrow